A Finding Aid to the Neil Juhl Larsen Research Material on Charles Biederman, circa 1927-2011, in the Archives of American Art AAA.larsneil
Archives of American Art
Neil Juhl Larsen research material on Charles Biederman
circa 1927-2011
AAA.larsneil
Archives of American Art
9.4 Linear feet
The Neil Juhl Larsen research material on Charles Biederman measures 9.4 linear feet and dates from circa 1927-2011. The material was compiled primarily by Neil Juhl Larsen in preparation for his biography, Charles Biederman (Hudson Hills Press, 2011). Also included is a small amount of material compiled by art historian Susan Larsen (no relation to Neil), who completed the book after Neil Larsen's death in 2006. The bulk of the research material consists of original papers belonging to Charles Biederman, including biographical material, correspondence, writings, personal business records, printed material, and photographs. These papers were given to Neil Juhl Larsen by Biederman and his daughter Anna Biederman Brown.
Larsen, Neil Juhl
Arrangement note
This collection is arranged as 2 series.
Series 1: Charles Biederman Papers, circa 1927-2004 (Boxes 1-6; 6.0 linear feet)
Series 2: Research Files, circa 1941-2011 (Boxes 7-10; 3.4 linear feet)
Conditions Governing Access note
Use of original papers requires an appointment and is limited to the Washington, D.C. Research Center.
Existence and Location of Originals note
Originals of document photocopies and photographs of artwork found in this collection are located at the Weisman Art Museum, University of Minnesota.
Immediate Source of Acquisition note
The collection was donated in 2012 by Susan M. Fridley, Neil Juhl Larsen's widow. Original material came directly from Charles Biederman and his daughter Anna Biederman Brown for the purposes of completing Biederman's biography and was compiled by Neil Larsen, and after his death, by Susan Larsen.
Related Archival Materials note
Also in the Archives of American Art are 23 reels of microfilm (reels 1446-1450 and 1662-1679) of the Charles Biederman papers, loaned for microfilming in 1978-1979. The Biederman papers are now located at the Weisman Art Museum, University of Minnesota. Additionally, the Archives of American Art holds the microfilm of the David Barr papers relating to Charles Biederman (reel 1294), and an oral history interview with Charles Biederman, conducted 1976 May 6, by Paul Cummings.
Biographical/Historical note
Neil Juhl Larsen (1956-2006) was a writer, artist, friend, and biographer of modernist painter and sculptor Charles Biederman (1906-2004). Larsen died in 2006 while preparing the biography, and the project was turned over to art historian Susan Larsen (no relation to Neil), who had written on Biederman as well. The biography, Charles Biederman, was published in 2011.
Scope and Contents note
The Neil Juhl Larsen research material on Charles Biederman measures 9.4 linear feet and dates from circa 1927-2011. The material was compiled primarily by Neil Juhl Larsen in preparation for his biography, Charles Biederman (Hudson Hills Press, 2011). Also included is a small amount of material compiled by art historian Susan Larsen (no relation to Neil), who completed the book after Neil Larsen's death in 2006. The bulk of the research material consists of original papers belonging to Charles Biederman, including biographical material, correspondence, writings, personal business records, printed material, and photographs. These papers were given to Neil Juhl Larsen by Biederman and his daughter Anna Biederman Brown.
Biederman, Charles Joseph, 1906-2004; Larsen, Susan C.; Modernism (Art); Painters--Minnesota; Photographs; Sculptors--Minnesota
- Charles Biederman Papers, circa 1927-2004; Series 1; 6 Linear feet Boxes 1-6
  Arrangement note
  The series is arranged as 6 subseries.
  1.1: Biographical Material, 1932-2004
  1.2: Correspondence, 1935-2004
  1.3: Writings, 1950-2004
  1.4: Personal Business Records, 1960-2001
  1.5: Printed Material, 1933-1996
  1.6: Photographs, circa 1927-2003
  Scope and Contents note
  The Charles Biederman papers consists of biographical material, correspondence, writings, personal papers, printed material, and photographs which were given to Neil Juhl Larsen during the course of his work on the book Charles Biederman. While most papers are original, some of the writings and correspondence are photocopies.
  - Biographical Material, 1932-2004; 1.1
    Found here is scattered biographical material regarding Charles Biederman including various resumes, chronologies and biographical content for Biederman's website. Also found are thoughts on Biederman written by his wife Mary, caregiver notes and recollections, a list of books in Biederman's library, and an oral history interview transcript. Researchers should note that additional documents such as one address book, estate and selective service records, and passports are primarily photocopies of originals.
    - Address Book, undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Archives of American Art Oral History Transcript, 1976 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Biographical Resumes and Chronologies, 1969-1976 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Books in Personal Library, 1999-2000 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Caregiver's Journal and Various Personal Recollections, 2002-2004 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Estate Planning, 1978 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Passports, 1932-1988 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Selective Service, 1941-1945 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Thoughts on Charles Written by Mary Biederman, 1936 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Website Content, 2001 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Correspondence, 1935-2004; 1.2
    The majority of correspondence is between Charles Biederman, his wife Mary, and daughter Anna. Included are "Morning Notes" which Biederman would write late at night in his studio and leave on the breakfast table for Mary and Anna to read in the morning. Many of these are illustrated. Also included is correspondence with Mary's brother-in-law and sister, John and Eugenie Anderson. John Anderson was also an patron of Biederman's early artistic work. Additional correspondence of note is with writers Leif Sjoberg, Joan Waddell Barnes, and artist Jean Albert Gorin. The bulk of the correspondence found here is either photocopies or typescripts of originals.
    - Anderson, John and Eugenie, 1935-1942 (Box 1, Folder 11-19)
    - Barnes, Joan Waddell - Excerpts from Letters, 1941-1942 (Box 1, Folder 20-21)
    - Biederman, Anna, 1952; 1955; 1961-1969 (Box 1, Folder 22-34)
    - Biederman, Mary, 1940 (Box 1, Folder 35-38)
    - Biederman, Mary, 1941-1974 (Box 2, Folder 1-18)
    - Biederman, Mary, undated (Box 2, Folder 19)
    - "Morning Notes" to Mary and Anna Biederman, 1950s (Box 2, Folder 20-24)
    - Gorin, Jean Albert, 1946-1952 (Box 2, Folder 25-27)
    - Minneapolis Institute of Arts, 1976 (Box 2, Folder 28)
    - Sjoberg, Leif, 1969-1979 (Box 2, Folder 29-30)
    - Zabriskie Gallery, 1972 (Box 2, Folder 31)
    - Miscellaneous Correspondence, 1940-2004 (Box 2, Folder 32)
  - Writings, 1950-2004; 1.3
    Writings include notebooks, notes, poetry, essays, and other draft writings by Charles Biederman. Most of the writings are on nature. Researchers should note that most of these documents are photocopies of originals, especially writings dating before 1995.
    - Notebook, 1950-1988 (Box 2, Folder 33)
    - Notebook, circa 2004 (Box 2, Folder 34)
    - Notes From Nature, 1957-1990 (Box 2, Folder 35-39)
    - Notes, 1960-2003 (Box 3, Folder 1-5)
    - Notes, circa 1995-1999 (Box 3, Folder 6-7)
    - Notes, undated (Box 3, Folder 8)
    - Poems, circa 1961-1976 (Box 3, Folder 9)
    - Journal LLL Art & Music, circa 1951-1953 (Box 3, Folder 10)
    - "Art and Literature as Creation", 1957-1959 (Box 3, Folder 11)
    - "The Creative Process of Nature", 1960 (Box 3, Folder 12)
    - "The Creative Structural Process of Nature Part II", 1963 (Box 3, Folder 13)
    - Various Writings, 1959-2003 (Box 3, Folder 14-25)
    - Writings by David Bohm, Annotated by Charles Biederman, undated (Box 3, Folder 26)
  - Personal Business Records, 1960-2001; 1.4
    Found here is a small amount of Charles Biederman's personal business records, including his dealings with the Archives of American Art and Weisman Art Museum, reproduction agreements, and deeds of gift for his artwork to various individuals.
    - Archives of American Art, 1973-1998 (Box 3, Folder 27)
    - Deeds of Gift, 1960-2001 (Box 3, Folder 28)
    - Permissions to Reproduce for Search For New Arts, 1976-1980 (Box 3, Folder 29-32)
    - Reproduction Agreements, 1976-2001 (Box 3, Folder 33)
    - Weisman Art Museum Agreements, 1991-2001 (Box 3, Folder 34-36)
    - Miscellaneous Business Records, circa 1992 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Printed Material, 1933-1996; 1.5
    Printed material primarily consists of exhibition catalogs and announcements for Biederman's work, as well as a few press releases, conference publications, and magazines. Also included is one book containing annotations by Biederman.
    - Annotated Book, Science and Sanity by Alfred Korzybski, 1933 (Box 4, Folder 2)
    - Exhibition Catalogs and Announcements, 1936-1941 (Box 4, Folder 3)
    - Exhibition Catalogs and Announcements, 1962-1996 (Box 4, Folder 4-14)
    - Press Release, 1965 (Box 4, Folder 15)
    - Pro Conference Publications, 1987-1992 (Box 4, Folder 16)
    - Magazines, 1966-1978; 1942 (Box 4, Folder 17)
    - Structure Magazine, 1958-1964 (Box 4, Folder 18-19)
  - Photographs, circa 1927-2003; 1.6
    Numerous photographs depict Charles Biederman, his wife Mary and daugther Anna, thier home and studio, and exhibitions of his work. Also included are photographs of friends and family and Biederman's 1988 trip to Europe, as well as photographs, slides, transparencies, and negatives of Biederman's artwork.
    - Charles Biederman, 1936-2000s (Box 4, Folder 20-26)
    - Charles, Mary, and Anna Biederman, circa 1940s-1960s (Box 4, Folder 27)
    - Charles Biederman with Others, circa 1927-1990s (Box 4, Folder 28)
    - Anna Biederman, 1940s-1960s (Box 4, Folder 29)
    - Others, circa 1927-2002 (Box 4, Folder 30)
    - Biederman Home and Studio, circa 1950s-2000s (Box 4, Folder 31)
    - Visit to Europe, 1988 (Box 4, Folder 32-33)
    - Exhibition Installation at Hayward Gallery, 1969 (Box 4, Folder 34)
    - Exhibition Installations, 1998; undated (Box 5, Folder 1-2)
    - Exhibition Opening at Cedar Rapids Museum of Art, 2003 (Box 5, Folder 3-4)
    - Miscellaneous Personal Photographs, circa 1940s-1990s (Box 5, Folder 5)
    - Photographs and Transparencies for "Search for New Arts", circa 1950s-1970s (Box 5, Folder 6)
    - Photographs of Artwork, 1938-1960s (Box 5, Folder 7-22)
    - Photographs of Artwork, circa 1930s-2002 (Box 6, Folder 1-14)
    - Photographs of Artwork by Others, circa 1950s-1960s (Box 6, Folder 15)
    - Photographs of String Reliefs, 1950s-1960s (Box 6, Folder 16)
    - Slides, circa 1958-1990s (Box 6, Folder 17-22)
    - Transparencies and Negatives, circa 1950s-1990s (Box 6, Folder 23-24)
- Research Files, circa 1941-2011; Series 2; 3.4 Linear feet Boxes 7-10
  Found here are Neil Juhl Larsen's research files regarding Charles Biederman compiled during his work on the book Charles Biederman, which was published in 2011 after Larsen's death. A small amount of material compiled or annotated by Susan Larsen for the completion of the book is also included. Files contain notes, annotated photocopies of original documents, articles on Biederman, photographs, and a small amount of correspondence. Research files document many aspects of Biederman's life and career, including extensive documentation on his artwork and writings, as well as related subject matter. Of note is a research binder belonging to Neil Juhl Larsen which includes original correspondence with Biederman, photographs, and other material documenting their collaboration on this book project. Researchers should note that much of the research material is photocopies which are often annotated by Larsen. Also included is a set of color snapshots of preliminary sketches, artworks on paper, designs, and drawings by Charles Biederman.
  - Architecture, circa 2000s (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - Art Production and Sales, circa 2002 (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - Articles about Charles Biederman (1934-1999), 1963-2000s (Box 7, Folder 3-18)
  - Awards, 1998-2000s (Box 7, Folder 19)
  - Background, Family, Youth, 2007-2009 (Box 7, Folder 20)
  - British Structurism, 1957-2000s (Box 7, Folder 21)
  - Copyright, circa 1979-2000 (Box 7, Folder 22)
  - Correspondence Regarding Book Project, 2001-2009 (Box 7, Folder 23)
  - Death, Wills, Etc., 1999-2005 (Box 7, Folder 24)
  - Exhibitions, circa 2000s; 2011 (Box 7, Folder 25)
  - Interviews, circa 2000s (Box 7, Folder 26)
  - Internet Articles, 2005-2009 (Box 7, Folder 27)
  - Inventory, Charles Biederman Preliminary Studies, 2005 (Box 7, Folder 28-29)
  - Jan Van der Marck Files on Charles Biederman, 1963-2005 (Box 7, Folder 30-34)
  - Jan Van der Marck Interview, circa 2000s (Box 7, Folder 35)
  - Jordan Court, 2000s; circa 1973 (Box 7, Folder 36)
  - List of Published Articles by Charles Biederman, circa 2001 (Box 7, Folder 37)
  - Mary Biederman's Journals, Excerpts and Photocopies, circa 2000s (Box 7, Folder 38)
  - Miscellaneous Articles, circa 1940s-2005 (Box 7, Folder 39)
  - Miscellaneous Documents, circa 1990s-2000s (Box 7, Folder 40)
  - Museums, 1996-2004 (Box 7, Folder 41)
  - North American Structurism, 2000s; 1968 (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - Notebook of Charles Biederman Quotes, 1998-2001 (Box 8, Folder 2)
  - Notes from Conversations with Charles Biederman, 2005 (Box 8, Folder 3)
  - Obituaries, 2004-2005 (Box 8, Folder 4)
  - Photographs of Artwork, 2000s (Box 8, Folder 5-20)
    Color snapshots of preliminary sketches, artworks on paper, designs, and drawings by Charles Biederman. Photographs also includes annotations by Biederman.
  - Photographs of Artwork, 2000s (Box 9, Folder 1-14)
  - Printed Material on Related Subject Matter, 1950-200s (Box 9, Folder 15)
  - Published Writings by Charles Biederman, 1942-2000s (Box 9, Folder 16-20)
  - Red Wing Public Library, circa 1990s (Box 9, Folder 21)
  - Reproductions of Artwork, circa 1990s-2009 (Box 9, Folder 22)
  - Research Binder, 1993-2000s (Box 9, Folder 23)
    Includes photographs, correspondence between Larsen and Biederman, and original writings by Biederman.
  - Research on Individuals (Box 9)
    - Joost Baljeu, 2006 (Box 9, Folder 24)
    - Joan Saugrain Brendendieck, 1965-2005 (Box 9, Folder 25)
    - Wilma Crittenden, 2000s (Box 9, Folder 26)
    - Jean Gorin, 2000s (Box 9, Folder 27)
    - Beatrice Chinnock Grabbe, 2000s (Box 9, Folder 28)
    - Malcolm McCannel, 1997 (Box 9, Folder 29)
    - George L. K. Morris, circa 1941 (Box 9, Folder 30)
    - Victor Pasmore, 1998 (Box 10, Folder 1)
    - George Rickey, 2000s (Box 10, Folder 2)
    - Jean Sabo, 2000s (Box 10, Folder 3)
    - Leif Sjoberg, 1998-2000s (Box 10, Folder 4)
    - Charles Stinson, circa 2000s (Box 10, Folder 5)
    - Jan Van der Marck, 2000-2005; 1966 (Box 10, Folder 6)
    - Aspasia Voulis, 1963; 2000s; 1966 (Box 10, Folder 7)
    - Gillian Wise, circa 1967; 2000s (Box 10, Folder 8)
  - Research on Writings (Box 10)
    - "Art As the Evolution of Visual Knowledge", 2000s (Box 10, Folder 9)
    - "Art As Humanization of Science", circa 1998 (Box 10, Folder 10)
    - "Nature Art Anew", circa 2000s (Box 10, Folder 11)
    - "The New Cezanne", 1958; 1975; 2000s (Box 10, Folder 12)
    - "Search For New Arts", circa 1981-1982 (Box 10, Folder 13)
    - "Visual Millenium", 2000 (Box 10, Folder 14)
  - Thesis, "The Art of Charles Biederman," David Lee Craven, 2006; 1979 (Box 10, Folder 15-16)
  - Thesis, "The Search for a Constructive Art," David John Barr (1965), circa 2000s (Box 10, Folder 17)
  - Visit to Europe, 2000s; 1988 (Box 10, Folder 18)
  - Weisman Art Museum, 1998-2005 (Box 10, Folder 19-20)
  - Weisman Art Museum, Inventory of Archival Material, 2005 (Box 10, Folder 21)
  - Weisman Art Museum, Memorial Service, 2005 (Box 10, Folder 22)